Was wünscht du dir für die Erinnerung an die Opfer und
Überlebenden des 7. Oktober?
Oh...
I hate it when they call us heroes...
Because if anyone had asked me,
if I am willing to go through that
I would probably say no.
We didn’t choose it.
We did choose to live close to the border,
but...
We had 100% faith that the IDF
will always be stronger than the other side,
and I must tell you something about this
I hear so many people around the world saying that...
"Oh really?",
"The IDF couldn’t stop them?"
That is the most racist thing you can say,
I know people from Gaza.
There are brilliant people over there.
How racist is that?
What? Because we’re Jewish and they're Arab,
that is unbelievable. I am feeling...
I'm ashamed for my Palestinian friends,
to hear people speak like that.
That particular day, they outsmarted us,
and anybody who thinks that is not possible is a...
that's racism of low expectations.
Excuse me, that's racism of low expectations.
There's no reason why it couldn’t happen.
So how should they remember us?
I think that people need to understand
what Israelis understand,
that if I didn’t live here,
the tunnels would go all the way to Sderot,
or Jerusalem.
For me as a Jew around the world today,
none of us, not the Middle Eastern,
not the North African and not the European Jews,
none of us are safe today.
We know that we need to protect our borders.
We have been living alongside
regimes that were...
most of them were very hostile for 75 years.
We need to keep the borders of our country protected,
because I have every right to live in the Middle East,
practicing my culture, my religion,
holding my head up high,
living in a Jewish culture and community.
I have every right to do that.
As an Israeli sitting here on the fence,
I don’t know if I'll be able to do that anymore,
but it is a very important thing to do,
it’s a very important thing to do.
We understand in the Middle East
what people around the world don’t understand,
because the Middle East used to be little tribes,
like you have today in
Europe and all around the world.
We used to be like that...
and if you look at the world map today,
and you look at the Middle East,
you will see that from all the ethnicities,
all the minorities, in the Middle East,
the Jews are the only ones that can rule a tiny
tiny piece of land in a world of,
in a region that is all ruled by proper Muslims.
And, you look around and you say
"What about all the rest of us?".
What about the Druze, the Yazidis,
The Baháʼís, the Berbers in North Africa,
the Copts,
the Kurds, the...
What about them?
All the Christians? What about all the peaceful Muslims?
All the moderate ones?
And, people around the world don’t understand that...
People look at the Middle East,
and they see Jews versus Arabs,
or Jews versus Muslims.
The Middle East is far more complicated than that.
And if you wanted to make a categorization,
and divide it into two,
it would be extremists versus moderates.
Israel today...
Is one of the strongest countries in the Middle East,
to help the entire Middle East
to fight that extremism,
that we see from so many sides here.
If you want just the just a few examples,
just look at what is happening with the Druze,
look at what is happening in Syria
See the Druze of Syria waving the Israeli flag.
Waiting for Israel to come.
There is a good relationship and cooperation between the Druze,
and the Jews and ...
the Kurds and when they can.
The Kurds, the poor Kurds,
that are persecuted in four different countries,
Not being able to practice their culture,
their religion.
Why people around the world don’t understand that
people have the right to self-determination
even if they're not Palestinian.
There are so many other ethnicities here.
What about us?
I'm the only one, the Jews are the only one that have
a seven-long-hour-drive country.
Seven-long-hour-drive. And if you think about this region,
if you take it back in time,
A few hundred years ago,
there were three little
religions that were created in this region.
Three little religions
three little dots on the world's map.
there was Judaism Christianity and Islam.
Two were developed in Israel,
one was in Saudi Arabia,
and it was like three little dots,
because there was this person with an idea,
and then came followers.
Now let's jump
Let's leap in time and look at the world map today.
The American continent...
100% Christian or almost, ruled by Christians.
Europe Australia...
New Zealand, all that part of the world.
Look at the Muslims, the entire Middle East,
vast parts of Africa, vast parts of Asia Pacific.
Look at the Jews,
we are the same little dots where we started.
right where we started.
We haven’t moved, we haven’t grown,
you can’t even write the name Israel,
you don’t have enough space on the world map,
so... I'm the imperialist?
those two religions each have over two continents, continents!
so me for the seven-hour-drive country...
I'm the imperialist? I'm the colonialist? seriously?
Is that a joke?
And people in Israel understand,
we understand that...
We understand the need to protect our borders,
and we understand the need,
if I wouldn’t protect my borders,
I will end up like the Kurds and the Yazidis,
and the Druze.
I will end up like them.
And if you want to compare and contrast,
take the Baháʼís. Take the Baháʼís,
go check what is happening with them in Israel,
and go check what is happening with them in Iran,
because in Israel you can be whatever you want to be.
A Druze, a Christian...
nobody gives a...
That's a completely different situation than other...
surrounding countries,
neighbouring countries. The other thing is,
there were people that asked me
"Why can’t you have this general regime here?",
"Where you have Muslims and Jews governing together?".
"Not saying that this is a Jewish state?" and blah.
I always tell them,
you find me one country in the Middle East,
one, that holds the same the same
human rights and freedom for a consecutive 75 years,
where you can be openly gay,
where you can be a divorced woman,
where you can be a single woman,
where you can be a woman, haha...
that doesn’t have that many upheavals,
and a change of regime
every once in a while,
there is not one country like that.
There are moderate countries in the region,
but you still can’t find a country where
for 75 consecutive years,
you had your freedom.
That question about our borders is,
I think this is the core essence
of the entire story
why we are so keen on protecting our borders.
Because if we didn’t have Israel in 2014
when we were attacked by radical Islam,
and we had a country and an army,
we lost 100 people.
The poor Yezidis who were also the same year,
at the same time
were attacked by radical Islamists,
and they went through a genocide.
Their people...
I can’t even speak about it, I want to cry,
their people, their children were sold as slaves.
Do you understand.
Thank God for the IDF.
And if somebody that lives thousands of miles away
wants to tell me how to protect my own children,
I am very willing to accept them here,
with their children, they can bring their children
and their grandchildren over here,
raise them where I raise mine,
and then we'll have a nice...
we'll sit on my porch, have a nice chit chat on
a glass of wine
on the fine arts of resilience and retaliation,
but until they do that, please,
please.
Don’t tell me how to
maintain the safety of my children,
my children.